# François Michonneau

francois.michonneau@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/francois-michonneau • https://francoismichonneau.net

**Leader, Engineer, and Educator** with 7+ years of non-profit and startup experience. Empathetic and curious, I thrive in collaborative environments to empower customers to get the most out of their data.

As a **people leader**, I have managed remote teams of 6 engineers and UX/UI designers. I enjoy leading the hiring process to assemble the right team to deliver projects on time.

With 20+ years of experience with R and a quantitative background (Ph.D. in marine biology specializing in biodiversity), I love analyzing data and understanding its value for making informed decisions. I have worked with PostgreSQL and DuckDB (with their respective geospatial extensions), and put in production Shiny applications on AWS using Docker. I have technical expertise in OLAP databases and in the Apache Arrow ecosystem.

Open source maintainer of several R packages, including {foghorn} and {rotl}, I specialize in developing interfaces to web API, and reproducible data pipelines.

Because data literacy is a life-changing skill, I have taught 25+ workshops worldwide and worked with online communities to empower researchers adopt data science and scientific computing best practices in inclusive learning environments.

Open for Remote work opportunities (based in France).

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Senior Training Engineer**

04/2023 - Present

#### Voltron Data • Remote

- Liaise with customers (pre-sales and post-sales) to gather their feedback and escalate issues with engineering
- Crafted and delivered training presentations about our products to 100+ partners' account executives worldwide
- Wrote an online book in collaboration with Engineers and Marketing team, driving website traffic by 50%
- Developed vision and multi-year roadmap to pioneer Training program

## **Lead Training Engineer**

08/2022 - 04/2023

## Voltron Data • Remote

- Led the development and delivery of webinars (150+ attendees) for open source tools (Python library Ibis), amplifying community engagement
- Wrote and edited 10+ how-to articles, demos, tutorials, and social media posts to drive adoption of open source tools in the developer community

#### **Senior Director Of Technology**

03/2020 - 08/2022

## The Carpentries • Remote

• Member of the Executive Team: managed day-to-day operations, led cross-team initiatives, developed strategic planning, oversaw hiring and onboarding, directly supervised 6 people

- Directed team of 3 engineers developing The Carpentries data management web app (Python/Django) to develop GDPR compliance features
- Led product and engineering for new curriculum infrastructure (R/RMarkdown + GItHub Actions), used across 100+ lessons with over 50k unique visitors/month
- Secured >\$400k in grant funding opportunities

## Curriculum Development Lead

02/2018 - 02/2020

#### The Carpentries • Remote

- Managed technical infrastructure, including migrating to cloud services (AWS) and Docker
- Developed monitoring system, dashboards (Shiny), and automated reports to increase reliability (99.9% uptime) and scale up our operations (50% year-to-year increase in the number of workshops)
- Coordinated 60+ community maintainers and oversaw the development of 10+ lessons

#### **Postdoctoral Researcher**

01/2015 - 02/2018

#### University of Florida

- Synthesized marine biodiversity records for the United States: using R (tidyverse, ggplot2, geospatial tools) and PostgreSQL to reconcile 3+ million records from 5 public databases using web API and web scrapping to identify knowledge gaps
- Led collaborative development of R packages to access biodiversity data through web APIs (5000+ monthly downloads, 360+ scientific citations)
- Designed and organized workshops and hackathons for biodiversity data digitization and analysis

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Doctor of Philosophy - PhD in Biology, Zoology

University of Florida 01/2006 - 12/2014

## Master's degree in Ecology, Biodiversity, Evolution

Pierre and Marie Curie University, Paris 01/2004 - 12/2005

## Master's degree in Tropical Biology

Université de La Réunion 01/2003 - 12/2004

## Bachelor of Science - BS in Population Biology

La Rochelle Université 01/2001 - 12/2003

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

## **RStudio Certified Trainer (tidyverse)**

04/2019 - Present

Posit PBC

## **VOLUNTEERING & LEADERSHIP**

**ROpenSci** 01/2024 - Present

Mentor

Mentoring members of the R developer community who are interested in writing, maintaining, or contributing to an R package.

The Carpentries 09/2014 - Present

Instructor Trainer, Lesson Maintainer, Instructor

- ► Instructor (2014-present): 25 workshops taught in the US, Europe, and the Caribbean.
- ▶ Lesson Maintainer for Data Carpentry R Ecology lesson, https://datacarpentry.org/R-ecology-lesson (2014-2023): This is the most taught and accessed Carpentries lesson (30,000+ unique visitors a month). Wrote the lesson and evaluated community contributions.
- ▶ Instructor Trainer (2017-2022): I teach the pedagogical concepts that used in Carpentries workshops to future instructors and participate in overseeing their certification process.

#### **SKILLS**

**Technical Skills:** Apache Arrow, Data Science, Docker, DuckDB, Git, Github + GitHub Actions, Jekyll, Linux (Ubuntu), R, SQL, tidyverse

**Leadership Skills:** Developer Advocacy, Pedagogy, Product Education, Product Management, Project Management, Remote Team Management